Guide to the Medieval manuscript fragments, [ca. 800-ca. 1800]
Medieval manuscript fragments
- Leaf from Lauda (song) book, from Italy., Early fifteenth-century.; Size: 214 x 147mm (146 x 90 mm). (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Description: Written on paper with no obvious water mark in Italian ottava rima. A single complete paper leaf, single columns written in a Textualis Formata script, in brown ink, ruled in plummet for 26 lines, 2-line initial in red at the beginning of each stanza; slightly faded and soiled, a few marginal losses (not affecting text), b ut entirely legible. A fragment of an unidentified Passion lauda comprising six stanzas in ottava rima. The lauda describes St. Peter’s denial, the trial of Christ before Caiaphas, the crowd’s verdict, the flagellation and the humiliation. The text, based on Matthew’s Gospel account, is presented as Christ’s own prophecy, narrated in the first person and in the future tense. The lauda is written in a literary vernacular which relies on a genre-specific, rather than a place-specific, vocabulary, but a few textual elements point to a mid-Italian origin (broadly Umbria, the March, or perhaps southern Tuscany); see ‘co[n]de[m]pnare’ (verso, line 2) and ‘collor’ (verso, line 8). Red capitals at the beginning of each stanza. Small, faint face illustration on first letter on final line on verso.
  Provenance: From the Rosenthal collection. Formerly 001.
- Will of Margarita de Ballis, of Alcamo, Sicily., 1408 (dated 1400 on page [3]).; Size: 310 x 220 mm (240 x 130 mm). (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Description: Written in Latin on laid paper. The last will ("est hec eius ultima voluntas") of Margarita de Ballis, the wife of the Count de Ballis, "[presens copia extratta] ex actis mei not[arii] Francesci ??? de alcamo." In Secretary hand. The de Ballis or de Ballo family, originally from Bologna, settled in Sicily in 1378 and in Alcamo ca. 1400. They built a fortified house in the 15th century which still stands. The watermark on this document, showing a hand with a flower, is common on paper throughout Europe.
  Provenance: Acquired in 2015 by Laurent Ferri.
- Notarial Act (Codicil to a Will) from Piacenza, Emilia-Romagna, Italy., Dated November 1419.; Size: 137 x 291 mm (99 x 246 mm). (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment. Donna Caterina, "vidua domini Antolini de Zonzeto", is leaving her silver girdle to be made into a chalice ("quod fiat mea centura argenti... unus calix argenti") for use in Santa Maria Nuova delle Virtú and Santo Spirito di Consorzio; also, asks that 43 lire due to her by the widow of Messer Antonio Chiochi, shoemaker, be distributed "among poor girls due to be married" (pauperes puellas maritandas"). The public notaries were Giovani Matteo (witness) and Castelino Corno, who signed with his personal device.
- Leaf from Old French translation of Pseudo-Bonaventure's Stimulus amoris, Northern France., circa 1420.; Size: 206 x 140 mm (146 x 76 mm). (Box 4, Folder 2a)
  Description: Written in Gothic script on ruled vellum, single column, 30 lines, with decorations. Decorations consist of two pilcrows in gold on pink and blue grounds with white lead penwork.
  Provenance: Acquired in 2016 by Laurent Ferri.
- Nine Leaves from a Book of Hours (Use of Sarum) Produced in England, ca. 1425 [colophon, 16th century].; Size: 240 x 170 mm, except last leaf, 190 x 156 mm. (Box 4, Folder 2bis)
  Description: Eight decorated folios + one leaf from an elegant English Book of Hours produced for some (endowed?) chapel in an English church or cathedral (rubrics on other leaves give instructions that the texts be read “sub silentio”)> A sixteenth-century inscription on the endleaf of the volume reads as follows: “Ye shall pray for the saules of Edward Cotterell & Margaret hys wyff, & of Roger, Thomas, John, William, Jane, Amey, Elizabeth, chylderyn of the seid Edwarde & Margaret”.
  Provenance: From the Library of Sir Robert Throckmorton (d. 1791; his armorial bookplate was in the volume sold in 2013). Then owned by John Meade Falkner (1858-1932), arms manufacturer and Librarian of Durham cathedral; auctioned by Sotheby's (12-14 December 1932, Lot 211) and acquired by H.R. Creswick (1902-88), Librarian of the Bodleian Library in Oxford, for his personal collection. After 1940 owned by Charles F. Cutts (1871-1949), and then by the Nevada Museum of Art, which sold it "to benefit the collections" (Christie's, 12 June 2013, Sale 1176, Lot 23. The catalog mentions 78+2 leaves bound in one volume).These leaves were eventually acquired in 2015 by Cornell. As of 2016, one other leaf is owned by the University of South Carolina, MS 138, and nine leaves are kept at Emory University, in the Pitts Theological Library, MS 370.
- Initial “E” with Adoration of the Magi taken from a choir book, possibly from Germany., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 144 x 141 mm (119 x 115 mm). (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Description: The burnished gold initial is set in a red field decorated with gold filigree designs. Vestiges of a green foliate border are evident in the upper and left margins. The interior of the letter is filled with a scene of the Adoration of the Magi. In the lower portion, two magi converse while the third kneels before the Virgin and Child sitting on a red bed. Joseph observes from behind a pillow on the left while two of the kings’ attendants hold a discussion on the right. The upper portion of the miniature contains the thatched roof of the manger, tan, conical hills with shepherds tending their flocks, two horsemen, a ploughman, peasants, showing their fields, a town and windmill, and copses of trees. In the pale blue sky are scudding clouds, birds in flight, and three hovering angels. The elegant garb of the Magi, their mincing poses, and the stylized landscape with its vestiges of realism link this miniature with the Internal style circa 1400 in France. However, the rough, sketchy style of painting, the nature of the decoration, and the form of the pointed script on the reverse suggest a German origin for the miniature.
  Provenance: Formerly Calkins no. 18; De Ricci II, 1237; folder 08.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_065_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_065_002.jpg (b).
- Foliate initial “C” from a choir book, from Italy., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 124 x 126 mm (112 x 112 mm). (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Description: A pink “C” on parchment decorated with white filigree, outlines in red and set against a burnished gold ground. Brilliant blue, green, and pink acanthus sprays emanate from the top and bottom portion of the letter. The tan ground of the initial sets off three luxuriant buds on stalks springing from a clump of varied leaves. Apparently cut from an Italian choir book, probably Lombard. The reverse side contains large gothic script, and square musical notation with red staffs.
  Provenance: Obtained in Europe circa 1895 by A. D. White. Formerly Calkins, no. 38; De Ricci, II, p. 1237; folder 07.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_067_001.jpg (a).
- Initial “E” with Adoration of the Magi from a choir book, from Northern Italy., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 259 x 222 mm (116 x 119 mm). (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Description: The letter “E” (116 x 119 mm) is made of thick pink, blue, and green acanthus sprays, while similar foliate decoration, arranged symmetrically, fills the left and bottom margins. The richness of the design, and the form of the curling acanthus is similar to Lombard decoration of the middle of the fifteenth century. This cutting is apparently from a lavishly decorated choir book. Both sides of the fragment contain large gothic script, and square musical notation with red staffs.
  Provenance: Obtained in Europe circa 1895 by A. D. White. Formerly Calkins no. 35; De Ricci, II, p. 1237; folder 06.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_066_001.jpg (a).
- Document with seal in Middle German., Fifteenth century.; Size: 283/240 x 479 mm (171 x 443 mm). (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Description: Document written in Cursiva script in Middle German on vellum. Green wax seal with figure of a saint remains attached on tag.
  Provenance: Formerly MS C82.
- One bifolium from a Psalter, from Northern Italy., Fifteenth century.; Size: 403 x 279 mm (255 x 190 mm) Four staves: 18.5 mm. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Description: Two leaves (one bifolium) written in Latin on parchment. Twenty one lines of text in two columns. A double folio which begins ‘Adoremus Dominum’ and ends ‘Et percussit inimicos’, containing the first part of Psalm 73 and a portion of the last half of Psalm 77. Initials in red and blue, decorated with pen flourishes. Some square musical notation in four staves on the recto of the first folio.
  Provenance: Obtained by A. D. White circa 1895. Formerly folder 02.
- Initial “S” from a Gradual from Germany or Bohemia., Fifteenth century.; Size: 181/175 x 191 mm (181/175 x 191 mm). (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Description: The letter “S” lavishly decorated with blue acanthus, is set against a burnished gold ground enframed with a red band. Red, blue, and white acanthus sprays curve through the interior of the design. Nude putti cavort among the foliage while a figure reads a book from a pulpit below. An infant figure of Christ holding a crossed orb appears above. High grade Gothic textura script on the verso, with musical notation.
  Provenance: Obtained in Munich in 1876 for A. D. White. Formerly folder 03.
- Remnant of a Book of Hours, annotated in the following centuries, with eight leaves (including three bifolia) in an eighteenth century binding, from France., Fifteenth century (and later annotations).; Size: Leaves all approximately 160 x 122 mm (99 x 71 mm). Binding: 172 x 122/280 mm. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Description: Remnant of a Book of Hours annotated and augmented in the following centuries, in numerous scripts (including Textualis Formata, Gothico-Antiqua, Hybrida Libraria) and written in Latin and French on parchment. Includes an inscription on the front pastedown dated 1768 naming one of its owners: Jean Hersmulle Duport, doctor of theology (Sorbonne), who taught physics at the Sulpician Grand Seminary of St Irénée, and then became curate of Loire, a village between Lyon and Vienne (until 1791). "Hic libris joannis hersmulle Duport... facultatis parisiensis doctoris theologi.. in ecclesia ligeriensis in diocesi viennensis [Vienne] anno 1768", with eight original leaves from the manuscript, most with added texts. The contents are: 1. one folio numbered 17, with the end of the Gospel lesson of St. Matthew, an inscription in a later hand, and on the verso the capital letters DE LH (the rest blank); 2. one folio with four lines of Latin religious verse in French Humanistic Minuscule script, below which is an erased inscription that can be read in ultraviolet light (naming “Jehan Frenier,” with various place-names: probably Je[h]an Frenier, curé de Saint-Martin de Maulay, near Loudun), the verso blank; 3. six folios from the end of the book, the first being the conclusion of the Suffrages but with the following added: a complete prayer in 90 rhyming couplets of French, beginning “O Iesu roy de tout le monde/En qui toute bonte abonde [Je suis ta pauvre creature/Contemplant ta saincte figure/Se tenant a grands cloux de fer... Helas quel fers, helas quelz cloux/Ils furent forges longs et groux/Pour te faire plus de martyre]” (a variant was printed in 1556 in Fr. Pierre Olivier, Le Mirouer du Chrestien -- Olivier was the spiritual advisor of Marguerite de Navarre -- he revised the Heptaméron), followed by “Les Sept Oraisons de St. Gregoire” complete in seven Latin stanzas; this followed by an inscription, “AU NOM DIEU / AMEN CES HEURES”. This remnant reveals the kinds of texts deemed essential in such books of private devotion but omitted, for whatever reason, from the original commission.
  Provenance: Acquired in April 2014 by Laurent Ferri.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_015_006.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_004.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_002.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_008.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_010.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_014.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_012.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_016.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_020.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_019.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_018.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_017.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_015.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_013.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_011.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_007.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_001.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_009.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_003.jpg; CornellMedMS_015_005.jpg.
- One account document from England., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 255 x 372 mm (232 x 280 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a documentary hand. Document listing money received and disbursed between April and August of 1434.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 58.
- Two leaves from a Book of Hours from France., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 154 x 108 mm (99 x 61 mm). (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Description: Written in Latin on fine parchment in a high-grade Textualis Formata (Textus Rotundus) script, from France (probably Paris). Smaller initials in gold leaf on blue and red backgrounds with white filigree. Two large gold leaf “D”s with the same type of background have decorative sprays of gold leaf pods and blue, red, and green flowers emanating from them into the margin. Folio 1 begins “Etenim correxit orbem terre” and ends, “orbi terre vidi et commota”. Folio 2 begins “in equitate et gentes in terra dirigis” and ends, “quoniam iudiicas populous”.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 18 (1-2).
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_004_004.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_004_003.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_004_002.jpg (2a).
- Leaf containing Marian prayers in German., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 138 x 111 mm (98 x 69 mm). (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Description: Prayers to the Virgin written in medieval German on parchment, with headings identifying the specific applications for the prayer, e.g. ‘Eyn gut gebeth zu unser lieber Maria…’. Single column, 34 lines. Foliated 47 (“xlvii.”) in upper margin. Used as a reinforcement in a binding, hence soiled and creased, with offsets in the margin and stitching holes in the center. Two initial O’s in blue, else rubricated in red ink.
  Provenance: Acquired 2013 by Laurent Ferri.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_005_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_005_002.jpg (b).
- Damaged document with very faded script., Possibly fifteenth century.; Size: 232 x 324 mm (124 x 282 mm). (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Description: Document on parchment, written in a documentary hand. Script is very faded and illegible, but evidence of raised ascenders on top line.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly e.56.
- Fragment taken from a binding., Possibly fifteenth century.; Size: 95 x 310 mm. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Description: Faded, mostly illegible script, probably in a chancery hand.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly b.56.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_012_004.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_012_004darker.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_012_003.jpg (b); CornellMedMS_012_003darker.jpg (b); CornellMedMS_012_002.jpg (c); CornellMedMS_012_002darker.jpg (c); CornellMedMS_012_001.jpg (d); CornellMedMS_012_001darker.jpg (d).
- Fragment taken from a binding., Possibly fifteenth century.; Size: 144 x 382 mm (85 x 120 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment. Faded, mostly illegible script, probably a Hybrida script. Ruling and a red capital “Q”.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly c.56.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_013_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_013_002.jpg (b, c); CornellMedMS_013_002_darker.jpg (b, c); CornellMedMS_013_003.jpg (d); CornellMedMS_013_003_darker.jp (d).
- Fragment from an unidentified book., Possibly fifteenth century.; Size: 129 x 56/35 mm. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Description: Badly damaged parchment fragment from a book removed from a binding. Only small section of faded text remains in a Cursiva script.
  Provenance: Formerly folder 56.k.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_007.jpg (a).
- Mutilated bifolia from the Speculum Doctrinale by Vincent of Beauvais., Fifteenth century.; Size: 72 x 339/172 mm (65 x 135 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Semitexualis Formata script. Text almost completely rubbed off, but red rubrication and paraphs still clear.
  Provenance: Formerly j.56
- Three nested bifolia of Statuta criminalia from Lucca, Italy., Fifteenth century.; Size: 362 x 271 mm (212 x 141 mm). (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Gothico-Antiqua script. Three bifolia forming most of a quire.
  Provenance: Brought in 1888 in Lucca, Italy, by George Burr for the President White Library. De Ricci B62.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_008_002.jpg (1a); CornellMedMS_008_001.jpg (1b); CornellMedMS_008_004.jpg (2a); CornellMedMS_008_003.jpg (2b).
- Two fragments from a glossed book., Fifteenth century.; Size: Fragment 1: 122 x 186 mm (94 x 109 mm one column). Fragment 2: 142 x 184 mm. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Description: Two fragments written in Latin on parchment and taken from the same glossed book, probably in a Semitextualis Libraria script. Taken from a binding.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly folder g.56 (1-2).
- Fragment from a book taken from a binding., Fifteenth century.; Size: 485 x 191 mm (407 x 177 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 13)
  Description: Written in Latin on thick parchment from a large book and written in a Hybrida Formata script.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly h.56.
- Fragment from the Codex Justinius, Book VIII., Fifteenth century.; Size: 298/270 x 234 mm (267 x 179 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 14)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Semitextualis Libraria script. Damaged partial leaf of Codex Justinius, Book VIII, probably parts 9-10. Red capitals and rubrication have survived better than the brown ink of the main hand itself, which is very faded.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly i.56.
- Leaf from a Rabbinic legal commentary, probably from Spain., Probably fifteenth century.; Size: 393 x 325 mm (263 x 209 mm). (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Description: Written in Hebrew on parchment. From a legal commentary text and probably concerning laws of damages. Taken from a binding.
  Provenance: Formerly folder O.
- Fragment of Isidore’s Etymologies, VIII 5.39-6.3., Fifteenth century.; Size: 282 x 204 mm (244 x 162 mm). (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a Gothico-Antiqua script in one writing block with no decoration.
  Provenance: Lost descriptions by Mary Wack, May 1978 and Robert Fagueira, June 1976. Formerly folder e.24.
- Two leaves from Cicero, Marcus Tulluis, Oratio pro Milano., Fifteenth century.; Size: Leaf 1: 339 x 216 mm (206 x 125 mm). Leaf 2: 338 x 204 mm (207 x 125 mm). (Box 4, Folder 17)
  Description: Both leaves are written in Latin on flesh side of parchment only in a Gothico-Antiqua script. Taken from a binding.
  Provenance: Restored and donated to Cornell by Mrs Fleda Meyers. Formerly folder f.1.
- Leaf from a highly decorated Book of Hours in Dutch, with illuminated initial “H” with crucified Christ., Fifteenth century.; Size: 174 x 125 mm (99 x 64 mm). (Box 4, Folder 18)
  Description: Written in Dutch in a Northern Textualis Formata script on parchment. Highly decorated on the recto with illumination of the crucified Christ with Mary, another saint (perhaps Mary Magdalene) and bird pricking its own breast; an angel on the edge of the right margin; and detailed calligraphic pen work.
  Provenance: Formerly Ferrini 64.
  ID Number: CornellMedMS_009_001.jpg (a); CornellMedMS_009_002.jpg (b).
- Leaf from Italian service book with illustration of St John with Lamb., Fifteenth-century.; Size: 318 x 232 mm (214 x 151 mm). (Box 4, Folder 19)
  Description: Written in Latin on high-quality parchment in a Textualis Formata (Rotunda). Highly decorated leaf with image of St John with lamb in initial “N” on the recto and an illuminated “L” on the verso. Alternating red and blue initials with decorative pen work and flourishes extending into the marginal and inter-linear space, red rubrication.
  Provenance: Formerly Ferrini folder 59 (Z 1).
- Two leaves, probably from the same Gradual from Northern Italy, with musical notation and decorated initials., Mid-fifteenth century.; Size: 71 (folio 222): 632 x 451 mm (441 x 320 mm). Four staves: 46.0 mm. 72 (folio 369):630 x 453 mm (436 x 306 mm). Four staves: 46.2 mm. (Mapcase-folder 2)
  Description: Both folios written in Latin in a Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script, on vellum. Folio numbered 222 begins “tabor in mandatis tuis”, and ends “consumationis vidi finem latum”. This folio contains on the verso a beautifully painted foliate initial “M” with a green acanthus spray in the margin. There are three other smaller decorated initials. There is square musical notation on red, four line staves. Folio numbered 369 begins “xi alleluia”, and ends “gaudebunt labia mea dum”. An initial “R” on the verso is enclosed in a field of carefully wrought pen scrolls and is accompanied by a semi-naturalistic foliate border with blue flowers. The size, format, ruling, script, and even the numberation of the folios of these two pages appear to be almost identical, suggesting that although the decoration is different, these leaves may be from the same choir book.
  Provenance: Obtained in Europe in 1878 by A. D. White. Formerly Calkins no. 32; De Ricci, II, 1236; folders 71 and 72.
- Three bifolia from an antiphonary from Northern Italy with musical notation and decorated initials., Fifteenth century.; Size: All approximately 561 x 404 mm (376 x 269 mm). Four staves: 34.5mm. (Mapcase-folder 3)
  Description: Three bifolia from an antiphonary with square musical notation on red, 4-line staves. Written in Latin in a high-grade Southern Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script on parchment. Leaves numbered 146 – 151. Red rubrication, and alternating red and blue initials decorated with pen flourishes. Text begins “Agnus coram tondente se” and ends, “Quem terra pontus ethera”, and contains part of the feast of the Annunciation of the Virgin.
  Provenance: Obtained in April 1885 for A. D. White from Dotti of Florence. Formerly Calkins, no. 37; De Ricci, II, 1236; and folder 70.
- Leaf from a Gradual with musical notation and decorated initials., Fifteenth century.; Size: 478 x 339 mm (391 x 246 mm). Four line staves: 21.5 mm. (Mapcase-folder 4)
  Description: Written in Latin in a (Iberian?) Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script. Folio 160 of a parchment gradual. Square notation on red, four line staves. Red rubrication and decorated initials.
  Provenance: Gift presented by H. Peter Kahn, March 20, 1991. Formerly folder 74a, Kahn no. 15.
- Leaf from a Gradual with musical notation., Fifteenth century.; Size: 545 x 382 mm (362 x 257 mm). Three staves: 22.5 mm. (Mapcase-folder 5)
  Description: Written in Latin on parchment in a high-grade Southern Textualis Formata (Rotunda) script. From a Gradual, with some square musical notation on red, three-line staves. Alternate red and blue initials, and red rubrication. Text on flesh side quite faded.
  Provenance: Gift presented by H. Peter Kahn, March 20, 1991. Brought in Rome. Formerly folder 74b.
- Fragment from a printed glossed book., Late fifteenth-century.; Size: 115 x 401mm (302 x 80 mm incomplete). (Box 4, Folder 20)
  Description: Heavily glossed book in Latin, printed on parchment.
  Provenance: Donated by Fleda Meyers. Formerly d.56.
- Historiated border from the Great Choir Book of Ferdinand and Isabella, Castile, Spain., Ca. 1479-1492.; Size: frame 510 x 260 mm (item 381 x 104 mm). (Mapcase-folder 8)